I used to get a lot of
questions about oil pulling.
So back in 2017 I did
a video series on it.
This video combines two
of those videos into one
looking at oil pulling
for oral health.
See the Doctor's Notes for the
other two videos in the series
and stay tuned for news
of an upcoming webinar
I'm going to be doing on bad breath
and the effects of tongue scraping.
Now to the video.
Flashback Friday: Oil Pulling Benefits for
Plaque, Gingivitis, Teeth Whitening and Bad Breath Tested
What are the potential risks and
benefits of the ancient practice
of oil pulling, in which
oil is swished or pulled
between the teeth for like
15 minutes and then spit out?
There are wild, unsubstantiated
claims online,
and even in the medical literature.
I can believe it's good exercise for
your tongue and cheek muscles,
but healing all organs simultaneously?
That statement seems a bit of a tongue
and cheek exercise right there!
Respondents in the British Medical
Journal expressed surprise
reading that swishing some
oil around in the mouth
could effectively treat diseases
like meningitis, heart, kidney,
hormone disorders. Oh, did
I mention cancer, AIDS, etc.?
Look, it may help in some way,
but for things to enter into
evidence-based medicine,
we actually need a little
something called evidence,
without being distracted by illusory
effects ascribed by their advocates,
especially when another
set of respondents
shared their experience of a case
of severe inflammatory gingivitis
that worsened after oil pulling.
She stopped and it got better.
They were thinking
maybe some of the oil
got like stuck under her gums.
Regardless, maybe
people should hold off
until we actually have
some evidence.
Thankfully, there's a Center for
Evidence-Based Medicine at Oxford
that recently compiled
all the controlled trials.
Why is it so important
there's a control group?
Because maybe the reported
declines in gingivitis and plaques
with oil pulling are just because
in the study they had dentists
looking over their shoulders
with constant check-ups.
So maybe the study subjects just
upped their brushing and flossing game.
This is the kind of study we need.
No changes before and
after in the control group,
but a drop in plaque and gingivitis
scores in the oil pulling group.
That's more like it.
OK, so there does
seem to be an effect,
but what do those numbers mean?
When you test a new
drug, it's not enough
to show it works better than
nothing, better than a sugar pill.
What you ideally want to know
is does the new drug work
better than the current best drug
out there, for the same condition.
Otherwise, what's the
point of a new therapy?
That's why drug companies are often
forced to use so-called active controls,
compare their drug not just
compared to nothing, a placebo,
but head-to-head against
the leading drug.
Here, oil pulling is
compared to doing nothing.
How about oil pulling
compared to chlorhexidine,
an antiseptic chemical used
in medicated mouthwash,
which is considered
to be a gold standard
in the fight against plaque,
cavities, and gingivitis?
So here we go.
Ladies and gentlemen, in one
corner, we have oil pulling.
In the other, chlorhexidine,
measuring their ability
to lower the number of
cavity-producing bacteria
on people's teeth, and...
Chlorhexidine worked faster,
a significant drop within just 24 hours
whereas, it took a week for the
oil pulling to really start working.
But by two weeks, the oil
pulling may end up
just as efficacious
as the gold standard.
In fact, they appeared
to work so similarly
skeptical me is critically
thinking, "Wait a second,
maybe it's just the physical act of
swishing that disrupts the plaque?"
It would have been cool if
they included a third group
that just swished with
water, and they did!
And swishing with
water had no effect.
Now, it wasn't exactly fair.
They had the oil pulling
group swishing for 10 minutes,
whereas the other two groups
only swished for one.
So for all we know, swishing
with water for 10 minutes
might be as good as the oil.
And one could look at this
and argue that chlorhexidine
actually worked 10 times
better, since it got
the same effect swishing
for one-tenth the time.
But chlorhexidine has side effects,
potentially serious side effects,
like painful desquamation, meaning
peeling of the mucous membranes
in your mouth, as well as
discoloration of the teeth or tongue.
So oil has certain benefits over
commercially available mouth rinses:
it's non-chemical, non-alcoholic,
low cost, and non-staining.
Yet the effectiveness is unclear.
But wait, oil pulling has been
shown to significantly drop
the number of cavity-causing
bacteria on the teeth.
Yeah, but does that translate
out into actual fewer cavities?
That's what we really care about,
but it hasn't been studied.
They did pair up oil pulling
versus chlorhexidine
against plaque and gingivitis,
and did find they were both
able to help to a similar degree,
and plaque-induced gingivitis
is a reasonable predictor
of future dental health, thereby
explaining the Oxford Center's
conclusion that oil pulling may indeed
have beneficial effects
on oral and dental health.
A review of the effects of oil pulling
concluded that the ancient practice
may indeed have beneficial effects
on oral and dental health.
I have talked about the benefits for
dental health, but oral health, too?
Oil pulling was also tested
against "oral malodor,"
also known as halitosis,
or simply, bad breath.
It's believed a quarter of the
world's population suffers from it.
So they decided to put oil pulling
versus chlorhexidine to the test.
How do you test for bad breath, though?
There's all sorts of really fancy
methods—gas chromatography,
electronic noses, diamond probes,
and dark field microscopy—
but these are really expensive,
or not very reliable.
So they decided to go
with the "gold standard."
Study subjects were just told
to breath in the researcher's face.
And then they wanted to know
what the study subjects thought
about their own breath, so they
asked them to lick their own wrist
and sniff it, then give it a score
from zero to extremely foul.
And though the subjects themselves
thought their licked wrists
smelled better after
two weeks of oil puling,
the researchers disagreed that
their breath smelled any better.
But after three weeks there was
a significant and comparable
improvement in breath odor in the
oil pulling and chlorhexidine groups.
I was excited about this study
because they used an actual placebo,
colored water, to presumably match
the look of the chlorhexidine,
and swishing for the same duration.
Aha! So we can finally answer
that nagging question
about whether oil pulling cuts
down on plaque and gingivitis
because of the oil, or just because
you're swishing anything
in your mouth that long.
And the water worked just
as well—the same drop
swishing with oil or just
swishing with water—
suggesting that the
plaque is just disrupted
by the extended rinsing action.
Yes, oil may be 5 or 6 times cheaper
than chlorhexidine and safer,
but cheaper and safer
than just plain water?
Yeah, but can water whiten teeth?
Numerous websites offer testimonials
of oil pulling whitening teeth, but
there were no studies published
in the medical literature, and so most
doctors would just give up there.
But these two dental professors
in Detroit decided to put it to the test.
Teeth were selected from
their stored collection
of human extracted teeth
(sounds a little horror movie-ish).
Then they put them in tubes
with coconut oil, sesame oil,
sunflower oil, along with some
fake saliva and vigorously shake
them every day for two weeks
and found... no evidence
to suggest that oil pulling has
any effect on teeth whitening.
That's like when another internet
darling was put to the test,
strawberries and baking soda, which
was evidently featured on Dr. Oz.
Over-the-counter whitening strips worked;
a home whitening system works,
where the dentist sends you
home with custom trays;
and in-office tooth
whitening works,
but the DIY strawberry
baking soda mixture failed,
as bad as just plain water
used as a control.
What about dental erosion?
In my video on plant-based
diets and dental health,
I talked about how those eating
healthier may have healthier gums,
but because they tend
to eat more acidic foods
like citrus and tomatoes, fruity teas,
they may be at more risk for
eroding off some of their enamel,
which is why we should
rinse our mouth with water
after eating or drinking
anything acidic, anything sour,
but what about rinsing
with oil every morning?
The way our body protects
our teeth from erosion
is by forming a "pellicle" over
our teeth, a protective layer
of mostly proteins from
our saliva, but some fat, too.
So, hey, might oil pulling
help prevent erosive damage
to our tooth surfaces by kind of
buttressing this protective layer?
You don't know until
you put it to the test.
Now they wanted to put the teeth
under a microscope afterwards,
and that's hard to do when
they're still in people's heads.
So they put slabs of cattle
teeth in their mouth,
let them sit there until that
protective layer developed,
and then oil pulled around the
teeth—or not in the control group—
and then took them out
and exposed them to acid.
If you expose the teeth to acid
without putting them in your mouth,
within 2 minutes, 120 seconds,
significant demineralization takes place.
Calcium is dissolved out
of the teeth by the acid.
But just let those same teeth roll around
in your mouth for a few minutes
and then expose them to
acid, there's less erosion.
OK, but then what happens if you put them
in your mouth and do some oil pulling?
Is there even less erosion?
No, there's more.
It's as if the oil pulling
undermined the protective layer.
And that's exactly what they
saw under the microscope.
Here's what that
protective layer looks like
before the oil pulling and then after.
They suspect the oil may actually
be depleting the protective
layer of some of its protection.